Guide to the American Association of University Professors: Rice University Chapter records, 1944-2004 (bulk dates 1960-2004) UA 096
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
American Association of University Professors: Rice University Chapter records
1944-2004
1960-2004
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
American Association of University Professors
UA 096
1 Linear Feet ( 2 boxes)
The American Association of University Professors: Rice University chapter collection consists of folders containing meeting minutes, correspondence, membership rosters, newsletters and other documents representing the regular business of the Rice University chapter. Specific issues covered in the collection are academic freedom and freedom of the press at Rice University.
Historical Sketch
In the early 1900's, university professors were limited in what they could teach and write. Many outspoken professors lost their jobs because of their views. The American Association of University Professors was born when Arthur O. Lovejoy, a philosopher at Johns Hopkins, and John Dewey organized a meeting at Johns Hopkins University in 1915 to form an organization to ensure academic freedom for faculty members. The mission of AAUP is to advance academic freedom and shared governance, to define fundamental professional values and standards for higher education, and to ensure higher education's contribution to the common good. AAUP is the leading organization primarily dedicated to protecting the academic freedom of professors. Faculty members turn to AAUP for assistance in the thousands each year. Membership in the national organization is open to all faculty, librarians, and academic professionals at two- and four-year accredited public and private colleges and universities. Membership as of 2004 is about 45,000, with over 500 local campus chapters and 39 state organizations. Leadership is provided by bi-annually elected national officers drawn from colleges and universities throughout the country. The Association is governed by an elected national Council that meets twice a year, and by an Executive Committee that meets four times a year.
Excerpted from http://www.aaup.org/aboutaaup/description.htm and http://www.aaup.org/aboutaaup/hist.HTM, [accessed June 10,2004].
Scope and Contents
The American Association of University Professors: Rice University chapter collection consists of folders containing meeting minutes, correspondence, membership rosters, newsletters and other documents representing the regular business of the Rice University chapter. Specific issues covered in the collection are academic freedom and freedom of the press at Rice University.
Access Restrictions
No access restrictions; this material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Arrangement
This material has been arranged in series chronologically.
Missing Title
Series I: 1944-47
Series II: 1960s
Series III: 1970s
Series IV: 1980s
Series V: 1996-2004
Acquisition Information
Transferred to the Woodson Research Center in 2004 by Dr. Ira Gruber, Harris Masterson Jr. Prof. of History.
Index Terms
Subjects
Academic Freedom; Freedom of the Press; Universities and colleges
Document Types
constitutions; reports; corrrespondence; financial records; clippings (information artifacts); minutes (administrative records)
Subjects (Persons)
Pitzer, Kenneth S. (Kenneth Sanborn); Davidson, Chandler
- Series I: 1944-47, 98817
  - Chapter meeting minutes notebook, 1944-47, 98818 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: 1960s, 98810
  Scope and Contents note
  Folders contain meeting minutes, correspondence, membership rosters, newsletters and other documents representing the regular business of the chapter. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Chapter's Constitution 1960-61, 98816 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes 1960-66, 98815 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pension File 1962-69, 98814 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Freedom of the Press 1964-65, 98813 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speakers and Academic Freedom 1964-65, 98812 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes 1967-70, 98811 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series III: 1970s, 98805
  - Minutes and Documents 1971-73, 98809 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Procedures 1974-76, 98808 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Rice Chapter 1978-79, 98807 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1979-80, 98806 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series IV: 1980s, 98802
  - 1981, 98804 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1982, 98803 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series V: 1996-2004, 98798
  - 1996-97, 98801 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1998-2000, 98800 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 2003-04, 98799 (Box 2, Folder 8)